<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Probabilistic Programming with GenJAX :: Probability &amp; Probabilistic Computing Tutorial</title>
    <link>http://localhost:45519/probintro/genjax/index.html</link>
    <description>From Probability Theory to Probabilistic Code In the previous tutorial, you learned to think about probability using sets and counting. Chibany showed you that probability questions are really about:&#xA;What’s possible? (Define the outcome space) What am I interested in? (Define the event) Count them! (Calculate the ratio) Now you’ll learn to express those same ideas in code using GenJAX — a probabilistic programming language that lets computers do the counting for you!</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:45519/probintro/genjax/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Getting Started with Google Colab</title>
      <link>http://localhost:45519/probintro/genjax/00_getting_started/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:45519/probintro/genjax/00_getting_started/index.html</guid>
      <description>What is Google Colab? Google Colab (short for “Colaboratory”) is a free online tool that lets you write and run Python code in your web browser. Think of it like Google Docs, but for code!&#xA;Why we love it for beginners:&#xA;✅ No installation needed ✅ No setup required ✅ Pre-installed with common libraries ✅ Free GPU access (for fast computation) ✅ Easy sharing with others ✅ Automatic saving to Google Drive Step 1: Open Your First Notebook Click this link to open the first GenJAX notebook:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Python Essentials for GenJAX</title>
      <link>http://localhost:45519/probintro/genjax/01_python_basics/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:45519/probintro/genjax/01_python_basics/index.html</guid>
      <description>You Don’t Need to Become a Programmer! This chapter teaches you just enough Python to read and run GenJAX code. You won’t become a software developer, but you’ll be able to:&#xA;Understand what the code is doing Modify values to experiment Run examples and see results Think of it like learning enough Italian to order food in a restaurant — you don’t need fluency, just practical knowledge!&#xA;1. Variables: Giving Names to Things In Python, we give names to values so we can use them later.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Your First GenJAX Model</title>
      <link>http://localhost:45519/probintro/genjax/02_first_model/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:45519/probintro/genjax/02_first_model/index.html</guid>
      <description>From Sets to Simulation Remember Chibany’s daily meals? We listed out the outcome space $\Omega = \{HH, HT, TH, TT\}$ and counted possibilities.&#xA;Now we’ll teach a computer to generate those outcomes instead!&#xA;The Generative Process Each day:&#xA;Lunch arrives — randomly H or T (equal probability) Dinner arrives — randomly H or T (equal probability) Record the day — the pair of meals In GenJAX, we express this as a generative function.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Traces</title>
      <link>http://localhost:45519/probintro/genjax/03_traces/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:45519/probintro/genjax/03_traces/index.html</guid>
      <description>What Gets Recorded When Code Runs? When you run a regular Python function, it does its work and returns a value. Then it’s done — no record of what happened internally.&#xA;GenJAX is different. When you run a generative function, GenJAX creates a trace — a complete record of:&#xA;What random choices were made What values they took What the function returned How probable this execution was Think of it like a lab notebook that automatically records every detail of an experiment!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conditioning and Observations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:45519/probintro/genjax/04_conditioning/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:45519/probintro/genjax/04_conditioning/index.html</guid>
      <description>From Simulation to Inference So far, we’ve used GenJAX to generate outcomes — simulating what could happen.&#xA;Now we’ll learn to infer — reasoning backwards from observations to causes.&#xA;This is the heart of probabilistic programming!&#xA;Recall: Conditional Probability From the probability tutorial, remember conditional probability:&#xA;“Given that I observed $B$, what’s the probability of $A$?”&#xA;Written: $P(A \mid B)$</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inference in Action: The Taxicab Problem</title>
      <link>http://localhost:45519/probintro/genjax/05_inference/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:45519/probintro/genjax/05_inference/index.html</guid>
      <description>Solving Real Problems with Probabilistic Code Remember the taxicab problem from the probability tutorial?&#xA;Scenario: Chibany witnesses a hit-and-run at night. He says the taxi was blue. But:&#xA;85% of taxis are green, 15% are blue Chibany identifies colors correctly 80% of the time Question: What’s the probability it was actually a blue taxi?&#xA;In the probability tutorial, we solved this with sets and Bayes’ theorem. Now we’ll solve it with GenJAX!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building Your Own Models</title>
      <link>http://localhost:45519/probintro/genjax/06_building_models/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:45519/probintro/genjax/06_building_models/index.html</guid>
      <description>From Following Recipes to Creating Your Own You’ve learned to use GenJAX through examples. Now it’s time to build your own probabilistic models!&#xA;This chapter shows you how to think about building generative models — turning real-world problems into code.&#xA;The Model-Building Process Step 1: Understand the Problem Before writing any code, answer:&#xA;What am I trying to predict or understand? (The question) What do I observe? (The data/evidence) What’s hidden? (The unknown variables) How are they related? (The causal structure) Example: Spam detection</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>