<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>A Narrative Introduction to Probability :: Probability &amp; Probabilistic Computing Tutorial</title>
    <link>http://localhost:43027/probintro/intro/index.html</link>
    <description>Welcome! This tutorial teaches probability theory through the story of Chibany (pictured below) who loves tonkatsu and wants to understand how likely they will get it in his daily meals. They hang out at the University cafeteria. Students offer him meals in bento boxes in the hopes that it will help them on their upcoming tests.&#xA;Along the way, you’ll learn to think about probability using sets: a perspective that makes complex concepts intuitive and prepares you for probabilistic programming and advanced applications.</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:43027/probintro/intro/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What You&#39;ll Learn</title>
      <link>http://localhost:43027/probintro/intro/01_goals/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:43027/probintro/intro/01_goals/index.html</guid>
      <description>This tutorial will give you a solid foundation in probability theory through a set-based approach. By the end, you’ll be able to reason clearly about uncertainty and be prepared for advanced topics in probabilistic computing and Bayesian inference.&#xA;Learning Goals 1. Think About Probability Using Sets Learn to see probability as counting: a concrete, visual approach that makes abstract concepts intuitive.&#xA;You’ll be able to:&#xA;Define outcome spaces (What could happen?) Identify events as subsets (What am I interested in?) Calculate probabilities by counting (What’s the ratio?) 2. Understand Core Concepts Through Narrative Follow Chibany’s story to master the fundamental building blocks of probability theory.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chibany is hungry</title>
      <link>http://localhost:43027/probintro/intro/02_hungry/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:43027/probintro/intro/02_hungry/index.html</guid>
      <description>Chibany wakes up from dreaming of the delicious meals they will get later today. Twice per day, a student brings them a bento box with a meal as an offering to Chibany. One student brings them a bento box in the early afternoon for lunch and a different student brings them a bento box in the evening for dinner. The meal is either a Hamburger or a Tonkatsu (pork cutlet) . To keep track of their meal possibilities, they list out the four possibilities:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probability and Counting</title>
      <link>http://localhost:43027/probintro/intro/03_prob_count/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:43027/probintro/intro/03_prob_count/index.html</guid>
      <description>One goal of this tutorial is to show you that probability is counting. When every possibility is equally likely, probability is defined as the relative number of possibilities in each set. When possibilities are not equally likely, it is only slightly more complicated. Rather than each possibility counting one towards the size of a set it is in, you count the possibility according to its relative weight.&#xA;Counting The basic operation that we use to define probabilities is counting the number of elements in a set. If $A$ is a set, then $|A|$ is the cardinality or size of the set.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conditional probability as changing the possible outcomes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:43027/probintro/intro/04_conditional/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:43027/probintro/intro/04_conditional/index.html</guid>
      <description>The Big Question Have you ever changed your mind about something after learning new information?&#xA;Of course you have! That’s what conditional probability is all about: how new knowledge changes what we believe is possible.&#xA;In this chapter, you’ll discover:&#xA;How learning something restricts the outcome space When events influence each other (dependence) How to calculate probabilities when possibilities have different weights Why your first intuition about conditional probability is often wrong! Ready for some surprising results? Let’s see what Chibany learns about dinner…</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayes&#39; Theorem: Updating Beliefs</title>
      <link>http://localhost:43027/probintro/intro/05_bayes/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:43027/probintro/intro/05_bayes/index.html</guid>
      <description>The Most Surprising Result in Probability Prepare to have your intuition completely shattered. 🤯&#xA;You’re about to discover why a positive medical test doesn’t mean what you think, why eyewitness testimony is less reliable than you expect, and why one of the most famous problems in probability stumps even experts.&#xA;In this chapter, you’ll learn:&#xA;How Bayes’ theorem updates beliefs with evidence Why base rates matter more than accuracy How to avoid the cognitive trap that catches almost everyone Why your first answer to the Taxicab Problem is almost certainly wrong! Fair warning: After this chapter, you’ll question your intuition about probabilities forever. Ready? Let’s meet Chibany on a foggy night…</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Glossary</title>
      <link>http://localhost:43027/probintro/intro/06_glossary/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:43027/probintro/intro/06_glossary/index.html</guid>
      <description>This glossary provides definitions for key terms used throughout the tutorial. Click on any term to expand its definition.&#xA;Core Concepts set set A set is a collection of elements or members. Sets are defined by the elements they do or do not contain. The elements are listed with commas between them and “$\{$” denotes the start of a set and “$\}$” the end of a set. Note that the elements of a set are unique.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <link>http://localhost:43027/probintro/intro/07_ack/index.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:43027/probintro/intro/07_ack/index.html</guid>
      <description>Written by Joe Austerweil. Thank you to Kyana Burhite, Hongtao Hao, and the many students who took Human and Machine Learning over the years who have provided invaluable feedback on an early draft of this tutorial.&#xA;Thanks to amplifier, which was used to help refine the tutorial content and generate the connecting GenJAX tutorials.&#xA;Further thanks to the Japan Probabilistic Computing Consortium Association (JPCCA) for funding my ability to polish and publish this tutorial series.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>